<chapter xml:id="ch_problemsolving" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Problem Solving</title>

	<introduction>
		<p>
			In previous math courses, you’ve no doubt run into the infamous <q>word problems.</q> Unfortunately, these problems rarely resemble the type of problems we actually encounter in everyday life. In math books, you usually are told exactly which formula or procedure to use, and are given exactly the information you need to answer the question. In real life, problem solving requires identifying an appropriate formula or procedure, and determining what information you will need (and won’t need) to answer the question.
		</p>

		<p>
			In this chapter, we will review several basic but powerful algebraic ideas: percents, rates, and proportions. We will then focus on the problem solving process, and explore how to use these ideas to solve problems where we don’t have perfect information.
		</p>
	</introduction>


		<section xml:id="sec_percents"> <!-- COMPLETE MS 1/2/2021-->
			<title>Percents</title>

			<objectives>
				<ol>
					<li>
						<p>
							Identify needed information and/or eliminate extraneous information towards solving contextual problems
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							Solve problems involving percents
						</p>
					</li>
				</ol>
			</objectives>
			

			<p>
				In the 2004 vice-presidential debates, Edwards's claimed that US forces have suffered "90% of the coalition casualties" in Iraq. Cheney disputed this, saying that in fact Iraqi security forces and coalition allies "have taken almost 50 percent" of the casualties (<url href="http://www.factcheck.org/cheney_edwards_mangle_facts.html">Source</url>). Who is correct? How can we make sense of these numbers?
			</p>

			<p>
				<term>Percent</term> literally means <q>per 100,</q> or <q>parts per hundred.</q> When we write 40%, this is equivalent to the fraction <m>\frac{40}{100}</m> or the decimal 0.40. Notice that 80 out of 200 and 10 out of 25 are also 40%, since <m>\frac{80}{200} = \frac{10}{25} = \frac{40}{100}</m>.
			</p>

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent1">
				<statement>
					<p>
						243 people out of 400 state that they like dogs. What percent is this?
					</p>
					<p>
						<m>\frac{243}{400}= 0.6075 = \frac{60.75}{100}</m>. This is 60.75%.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<p>
				Notice that the percent can be found from the equivalent decimal by moving the decimal point two places to the right.
			</p>

			<video youtube="Z229RysttR8"/>  <!-- Review of basic percents -->


			<remark xml:id="ex_percent2">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Write each as a percent: a) <m>\frac14</m> b) 0.02 c) 2.35
					</p>
					<p>
						a) = 25% b) 0.02 = 2% c) 2.35 = 235%
					</p>					
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<definition xml:id="def_percent">
				<title>Percent</title>
				<statement>
					<p>If we have a <em>part</em> that is some <em>percent</em> of a <em>whole</em>, then <me>\text{percent} = \frac{\text{part}}{\text{whole}}</me> or, equivalently, <me>\text{part} = \text{percent}\cdot\text{whole}.</me>
					To do the calculations, we write the percent as a decimal.						
					</p>
				</statement>
			</definition>
			
			<remark xml:id="ex_percent3">
				<statement>
					<p>
						The sales tax in a town is 9.4%. How much tax will you pay on a $140 purchase?
					</p>
					<p>
						Here, $140 is the whole, and we want to find 9.4% <em>of</em> $140. We start by writing the percent as a decimal by moving the decimal point two places to the left (which is equivalent to dividing by 100). We can then compute: <me>\text{tax} = 0.094(\$140) = \$13.16 \quad \text{in tax.}</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<video youtube="QjVeurkg8CQ"/> <!-- Absolute and Relative Differences -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent4">
				<statement>
					<p>
						In the news, you hear <q>tuition is expected to increase by 7% next year.</q> If tuition this year was $1200 per quarter, what will it be next year?
					</p>
					<p>
						The tuition next year will be the current tuition plus an additional 7%, so it will be 107% of this year’s tuition: <me> \$1200 \bigl(1.07\bigr) = \$1284.</me>
					</p>
					<p>
						Alternatively, we could have first calculated 7% of $1200: <m>\$1200(0.07) = \$84</m>.
					</p>
					<p>
						Notice this is <em>not</em> the expected tuition for next year (we could only wish). Instead, this is the expected <em>increase</em>, so to calculate the expected tuition, we’ll need to add this change to the previous year’s tuition: <me>\$1200 + \$84 = \$1284.</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<problem xml:id="tin_percent1">
				<statement>
					<p>
						A TV originally priced at $799 is on sale for 30% off. There is then a 9.2% sales tax. Find the price after including the discount and sales tax.
					</p>
				</statement>
				<answer>
					<p>The sale price is <m>\$799(0.70) = \$559.30</m>. After tax, the price is<m>\$559.30(1.092) = \$610.76</m>.						
					</p>
				</answer>
			</problem>

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent5">
				<statement>
					<p>
						The value of a car dropped from $7400 to $6800 over the last year. What percent decrease is this?
					</p>

					<p>
						To compute the percent change, we first need to find the dollar value change: <me>\$6800-\$7400 = -\$600.</me> Often we will take the absolute value of this amount, which is called the <term>absolute change</term>: <me>\bigl| -600\bigr| = 600.</me>
					</p>
					<p>
						Since we are computing the decrease relative to the starting value, we compute this percent out of $7400: <me>\frac{600}{7400}=0.081=8.1% \quad \text{decrease}.</me>
						This is called a <term>relative change</term>.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<definition xml:id="def_absolute">
				<title>Absolute and Relative Change</title>
				<statement>
					<p>Given two quantities,
						<md><mrow>\text{Absolute change} &amp;= \bigl| \text{ending quantity} - \text{starting quantity}\bigr|</mrow>
						<mrow>\text{Relative change} &amp;= \frac{\text{absolute change}}{\text{starting quantity}}</mrow></md>
					</p>
					<p>
						Absolute change has the same units as the original quantity.
					</p>

					<p>
						Relative change gives a percent change.
					</p>

					<p>
						The starting quantity is called the <term>base</term> of the percent change.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</definition>

			<video youtube="nygw69JqwoQ"/> <!-- Importance of Base in Percents -->

			<p>
				The base of a percent is very important. For example, while Nixon was president, it was argued that marijuana was a <q>gateway</q> drug, claiming that 80% of marijuana smokers went on to use harder drugs like cocaine. The problem is, this isn’t true. The true claim is that 80% of harder drug users first smoked marijuana. The difference is one of base: 80% of marijuana smokers using hard drugs, vs. 80% of hard drug users having smoked marijuana. These numbers are not equivalent. As it turns out, only one in 2,400 marijuana users actually go on to use harder drugs. (<url href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/LiesDamnedLiesAndStatistics">Source</url>)
			</p>

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent6">
				<statement>
					<p>
						There are about 75 QFC supermarkets in the U.S. Albertsons has about 215 stores. Compare the size of the two companies.
					</p>
					<p>
						When we make comparisons, we must ask first whether an absolute or relative comparison. The absolute difference is <me>215 – 75 = 140.</me> From this, we could say <q>Albertsons has 140 more stores than QFC.</q> However, if you wrote this in an article or paper, that number does not mean much. The relative difference may be more meaningful. There are two different relative changes we could calculate, depending on which store we use as the base:
					</p>
					<p>
						Using QFC as the base, <m> \frac{140}{75}=1.867.</m>
					</p>
					<p>
						This tells us Albertsons is 186.7% larger than QFC.
					</p>
					<p>
						Using Albertsons as the base, <m>\frac{140}{215}=0.651.</m>
					</p>
					<p>
						This tells us QFC is 65.1% smaller than Albertsons.
					</p>
					<p>
						Notice both of these are showing percent <em>differences</em>. We could also calculate the size of Albertsons relative to QFC: <m>\frac{215}{75}=2.867</m>, which tells us Albertsons is 2.867 times the size of QFC. Likewise, we could calculate the size of QFC relative to Albertsons: <m>\frac{75}{215}=0.349</m>, which tells us that QFC is 34.9% of the size of Albertsons.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<video youtube="4HNxwYMTNl8"/> <!-- Combining Percents -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent7">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Suppose a stock drops in value by 60% one week, then increases in value the next week by 75%. Is the value higher or lower than where it started?
					</p>
					<p>
						To answer this question, suppose the value started at $100. After one week, the value dropped by 60%: <me>	\$100 - \$100(0.60) = \$100 - \$60 = \$40.</me>
					</p>
					<p>
						In the next week, notice that base of the percent has changed to the new value, $40. Computing the 75% increase: <me>\$40 + \$40(0.75) = \$40 + \$30 = \$70.</me>
					</p>
					<p>
						In the end, the stock is still $30 lower, or 30% lower, valued than it started.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<problem xml:id="tin_percent2">
				<statement>
					<p>
						The U.S. federal debt at the end of 2001 was $5.77 trillion, and grew to $6.20 trillion by the end of 2002. At the end of 2005 it was $7.91 trillion, and grew to $8.45 trillion by the end of 2006. (<url href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/omb/budget/fy2013/assets/hist07z1.xls">Source</url>)
					</p>
					
					<p>Calculate the absolute and relative increase for 2001-2002 and 2005-2006. Which year saw a larger increase in federal debt?
					</p>
				</statement>
				<answer>
					<p>2001-2002: Absolute change: $0.43 trillion. Relative change: 7.45%</p>
					<p>2005-2006: Absolute change: $0.54 trillion. Relative change: 6.83%</p>
					<p>2005-2006 saw a larger absolute increase, but a smaller relative increase.</p>					
				</answer>
			</problem>

			<video youtube="Svlu2Lurmsc"/> <!-- Evaluating claims involving percents -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent8">
				<statement>
					<p>
						A Seattle Times article on high school graduation rates reported <q>The number of schools graduating 60 percent or fewer students in four years – sometimes referred to as <q>dropout factories</q> – decreased by 17 during that time period. The number of kids attending schools with such low graduation rates was cut in half.</q>
					</p>
					<p>
						a) Is the <q>decrease by 17</q> number a useful comparison?
					</p>

					<p>
						b) Considering the last sentence, can we conclude that the number of <q>dropout factories</q> was originally 34?
					</p>
					<p>
						a) This number is hard to evaluate, since we have no basis for judging whether this is a larger or small change. If the number of <q>dropout factories</q> dropped from 20 to 3, that’d be a very significant change, but if the number dropped from 217 to 200, that’d be less of an improvement.
					</p>

					<p>
						b) The last sentence provides relative change which helps put the first sentence in perspective. We can estimate that the number of <q>dropout factories</q> was probably previously around 34. However, it’s possible that students simply moved schools rather than the school improving, so that estimate might not be fully accurate.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent9">
				<statement>
					<p>
						In the 2004 vice-presidential debates, Edwards's claimed that US forces have suffered "90% of the coalition casualties" in Iraq. Cheney disputed this, saying that in fact Iraqi security forces and coalition allies "have taken almost 50 percent" of the casualties. Who is correct?
					</p>

					<p>
						Without more information, it is hard for us to judge who is correct, but we can easily conclude that these two percents are talking about different things, so one does not necessarily contradict the other. Edward’s claim was a percent with coalition forces as the base of the percent, while Cheney’s claim was a percent with both coalition and Iraqi security forces as the base of the percent. It turns out both statistics are in fact fairly accurate.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<problem xml:id="tin_percent3">
				<statement>
					<p>
						In the 2012 presidential elections, one candidate argued that <q>the president’s plan will cut $716 billion from Medicare, leading to fewer services for seniors,</q> while the other candidate rebuts that <q>our plan does not cut current spending and actually expands benefits for seniors, while implementing cost saving measures.</q> Are these claims in conflict, in agreement, or not comparable because they’re talking about different things?
					</p>
				</statement>
				<answer>
					<p>Without more information, it is hard to judge these arguments. This is compounded by the complexity of Medicare. As it turns out, the $716 billion is not a cut in current spending, but a cut in future increases in spending, largely reducing future growth in health care payments. In this case, at least the numerical claims in both statements could be considered at least partially true. Here is one source of more information if you’re interested: <url href="http://factcheck.org/2012/08/a-campaign-full-of-mediscare/"/>						
					</p>
				</answer>
			</problem>

			<p>
				We’ll wrap up our review of percents with a couple cautions. First, when talking about a change of quantities that are already measured in percents, we have to be careful in how we describe the change.
			</p>

			<video youtube="vtgEkQUB5F8"/> <!-- Percentage points and averaging percents -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent10">
				<statement>
				<p>
					A politician’s support increases from 40% of voters to 50% of voters. Describe the change.
				</p>		
				<p>
						We could describe this using an absolute change: <me>\bigl| 50\% - 40\% \bigr| = 10\%.</me> Notice that since the original quantities were percents, this change also has the units of percent. In this case, it is best to describe this as an increase of 10 <term>percentage points</term>.
					</p>
					<p>
						In contrast, we could compute the percent change: <me> \frac{10\%}{40\%} = 0.25 = 25\% \text{ increase.}</me> This is the relative change, and we’d say the politician’s support has increased by 25%.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<p>
				Lastly, a caution against averaging percents.
			</p>

			<remark xml:id="ex_percent11">
				<statement>
					<p>
						A basketball player scores on 40% of 2-point field goal attempts, and on 30% of 3-point of field goal attempts. Find the player’s overall field goal percentage.
					</p>

					<p>
						It is very tempting to average these values, and claim the overall average is 35%, but this is likely not correct, since most players make many more 2-point attempts than 3-point attempts.</p>
						
					<p>
						 We don’t actually have enough information to answer the question. Suppose the player attempted 200 2-point field goals and 100 3-point field goals. Then they made <m>200(0.40) = 80</m> 2-point shots and <m>100(0.30) = 30</m> 3-point shots. Overall, they made 110 shots out of 300, for a <me>\frac{110}{300}=0.367= 36.7\% \text{ overall field goal percentage.}</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<exercises xml:id="exercises_percents"> <!-- Numbers 1 Through 26 -->
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
						Out of 230 racers who started the marathon, 212 completed the race, 14 gave up, and 4 were disqualified. What percentage did not complete the marathon?
					</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Patrick left an $8 tip on a $50 restaurant bill. What percent tip is that?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Ireland has a 23% VAT (value-added tax, similar to a sales tax). How much will the VAT be on a purchase of a €250 item?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Employees in 2012 paid 4.2% of their gross wages towards social security (FICA tax), while employers paid another 6.2%. How much will someone earning $45,000 a year pay towards social security out of their gross wages?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A project on Kickstarter.com was aiming to raise $15,000 for a precision coffee press. They ended up with 714 supporters, raising 557% of their goal. How much did they raise?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Another project on Kickstarter for an iPad stylus raised 1,253% of their goal, raising a total of $313,490 from 7,511 supporters. What was their original goal?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The population of a town increased from 3,250 in 2008 to 4,300 in 2010. Find the absolute and relative (percent) increase.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							<url href="http://www.cnn.com/2010/SHOWBIZ/Music/07/19/cd.digital.sales/index.html">The number of CDs sold in 2010</url> was 114 million, down from 147 million the previous year. Find the absolute and relative (percent) decrease.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A company wants to decrease their energy use by 15%.
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										If their electric bill is currently $2,200 a month, what will their bill be if they’re successful?

									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										If their next bill is $1,700 a month, were they successful? Why or why not?
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A store is hoping an advertising campaign will increase their number of customers by 30%. They currently have about 80 customers a day.
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										How many customers will they have if their campaign is successful?
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										If they increase to 120 customers a day, were they successful? Why or why not?
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							An article reports <q>attendance dropped 6% this year, to 300.</q> What was the attendance before the drop?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							An article reports <q>sales have grown by 30% this year, to $200 million.</q> What were sales before the growth?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The Walden University had 47,456 students in 2010, while Kaplan University had 77,966 students. Complete the following statements:
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										Kaplan’s enrollment was ___% larger than Walden’s.
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										Walden’s enrollment was ___% smaller than Kaplan’s.
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										Walden’s enrollment was ___% of Kaplan’s.
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							In the 2012 Olympics, Usain Bolt ran the 100m dash in 9.63 seconds. Jim Hines won the 1968 Olympic gold with a time of 9.95 seconds.
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										Bolt’s time was ___% faster than Hines’.
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										Hines’ time was ___% slower than Bolt’s.
									</p>
								</li>
							 	<li>
									<p>
										Hines’ time was ___% of Bolt’s.
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A store has clearance items that have been marked down by 60%. They are having a sale, advertising an additional 30% off clearance items. What percent of the original price do you end up paying?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Which is better: having a stock that goes up 30% on Monday than drops 30% on Tuesday, or a stock that drops 30% on Monday and goes up 30% on Tuesday? In each case, what is the net percent gain or loss?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Are these two claims equivalent, in conflict, or not comparable because they’re talking about different things?
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>16.3% of Americans are without health insurance</q> (<url href="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/27/politics/btn-health-care/index.html">Source</url>)
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>only 55.9% of adults receive employer provided health insurance</q> (<url href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0712/78134.html">Source</url>)
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Are these two claims equivalent, in conflict, or not comparable because they’re talking about different things?
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>We mark up the wholesale price by 33% to come up with the retail price</q>
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>The store has a 25% profit margin</q>
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Are these two claims equivalent, in conflict, or not comparable because they’re talking about different things?
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>Every year since 1950, the number of American children gunned down has doubled.</q>
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>The number of child gunshot deaths has doubled from 1950 to 1994.</q>
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Are these two claims equivalent, in conflict, or not comparable because they’re talking about different things? (<url href="http://factcheck.org/2012/07/twisting-health-care-taxes/">Source</url>)
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>75 percent of the federal health care law’s taxes would be paid by those earning less than $120,000 a year</q>
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>76 percent of those who would pay the penalty [health care law’s taxes] for not having insurance in 2016 would earn under $120,000</q>
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Are these two claims equivalent, in conflict, or not comparable because they’re talking about different things?
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>The school levy is only a 0.1% increase of the property tax rate.</q>
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										<q>This new levy is a 12% tax hike, raising our total rate to $9.33 per $1000 of value.</q>
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Are the values compared in this statement comparable or not comparable? <q>Guns have murdered more Americans here at home in recent years than have died on the battlefields of Iraq and Afghanistan. In support of the two wars, more than 6,500 American soldiers have lost their lives. During the same period, however, guns have been used to murder about 100,000 people on American soil</q>. (<url href="http://www.northjersey.com/news/opinions/lautenberg_073112.html?c=y&amp;page=2">Source</url>)
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A high school currently has a 30% dropout rate. They’ve been tasked to decrease that rate by 20%. Find the equivalent percentage point drop.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A politician’s support grew from 42% by 3 percentage points to 45%. What percent (relative) change is this?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Marcy has a 70% average in her class going into the final exam. She says "I need to get a 100% on this final so I can raise my score to 85%." Is she correct?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Suppose you have one quart of water/juice mix that is 50% juice, and you add 2 quarts of juice. What percent juice is the final mix?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>

			</exercises>

		</section> <!-- Percent -->

		<section xml:id="sec_proportions"> <!-- COMPLETE MS 1/3/2021 -->
			<title>Proportions and Rates</title>

			<objectives>
				<ol>
					<li>
						<p>
							Identify needed information and/or eliminate extraneous information towards solving contextual problems
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							Recognize proportional relationships from verbal, graphical, symbolic or numerical scenarios
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							Use proportionality to solve and analyze a variety of multi-step contextual problems
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							4) Solve problems involving proportions and unit conversions
						</p>
					</li>
				</ol>
			</objectives>
			

			<p>
				If you wanted to power the city of Seattle using wind power, how many windmills would you need to install? Questions like these can be answered using rates and proportions.
			</p>

			<definition xml:id="def_rates">
				<title>Rates</title>
				<statement>
					<p>
						A rate is the ratio (fraction) of two quantities.
					</p>

					<p>
						A <term>unit rate</term> is a rate with a denominator of one.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</definition>

			<video youtube="aZrio6ztHKE"/> <!-- Basic rates and proportions -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates12">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Your car can drive 300 miles on a tank of 15 gallons. Express this as a rate.
					</p>

					<p>
						Expressed as a rate, <m>\frac{\text{300 miles}}{\text{15 gallons}}</m>. We can divide to find a unit rate: <m>\frac{\text{20 miles}}{\text{1 gallon}}</m>, which we could also write as <m>20\, \frac{\text{miles}}{\text{gallon}}</m>, or just 20 miles per gallon.
					</p>	
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<definition xml:id="def_proportion">
				<title>Proportion Equation</title>
				<statement>
					<p>
						A proportion equation is an equation showing the equivalence of two rates or ratios.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</definition>

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates13">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Solve the proportion <m>\displaystyle\frac{5}{3} = \displaystyle\frac{x}{6}</m> for the unknown value <em>x</em>.
					</p>
					<p>
						This proportion is asking us to find a fraction with denominator 6 that is equivalent to the fraction <m>\frac53</m>. We can solve this by multiplying both sides of the equation by 6, giving <me>x = \frac53 \cdot 6 = 10.</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates14">
				<statement>
					<p>
						A map scale indicates that <m>\frac12</m> inch on the map corresponds with 3 real miles. How many miles apart are two cities that are <m>2\frac14</m>inches apart on the map?
					</p>
					<p>
						We can set up a proportion by setting equal two rates, and introducing a variable, <em>x</em>, to represent the unknown quantity – the mile distance between the cities.
					</p>
					<md>
						<mrow> \frac{ \frac12 \text{ map inch}}{ 3 \text{ miles}} &amp;= \frac{ 2\frac14 \text{ map inch}}{ x \text{ miles}} &amp; \text{Multiply both sides by }x </mrow>
						<mrow> &amp;&amp; \text{and rewrite the mixed number}</mrow>
						<mrow> \frac{ 1/2 }{3} \cdot x &amp;= \frac94 &amp; \text{Multiply both sides by 3}</mrow>
						<mrow>\frac12 x &amp;= \frac{27}{4} &amp; \text{Multiply both sides by 2 (or divide by }\frac12 \text{)}</mrow>
						<mrow>x &amp;= \frac{27}{2} = 13\frac12 \text{ miles}.</mrow>
					</md>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<p>
				Many proportion problems can also be solved using <term>dimensional analysis</term>, the process of multiplying a quantity by rates to change the units.
			</p>

			<video youtube="jYwi3YqP0Wk"/> <!-- Proportions using dimensional analysis -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates15">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Your car can drive 300 miles on a tank of 15 gallons. How far can it drive on 40 gallons?
					</p>
					<p>
						We could certainly answer this question using a proportion: <me> \frac{300 \text{ miles}}{15 \text{ gallons}} = \frac{x \text{ miles}}{40 \text{ gallons}}.</me>
					</p>
					<p>
						However, we earlier found that 300 miles on 15 gallons gives a rate of 20 miles per gallon. If we multiply the given 40 gallon quantity by this rate, the <em>gallons</em> unit <q>cancels</q> and we’re left with a number of miles: <me>40\text{ gallons} \cdot \frac{20 \text{ miles}}{\text{gallon}} = \frac{40 \text{ gallons}}{1} \cdot \frac{20 \text{ miles}}{\text{gallon}} = 800 \text{ miles}.</me>
					</p>
					<p>
						Notice if instead we were asked <q>how many gallons are needed to drive 50 miles?</q> we could answer this question by inverting the 20 mile per gallon rate so that the <em>miles</em> unit cancels and we’re left with gallons: <me>50\text{ miles} \cdot \frac{1\text{ gallon}}{20\text{ miles}} = \frac{50\text{ miles}}{1} \cdot \frac{1\text{ gallon}}{20\text{ miles}} = \frac{50\text{ gallons}}{20} = 2.5\text{ gallons}.</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<p>
				Dimensional analysis can also be used to do unit conversions. Here are some unit conversions for reference.
			</p>
			
			<table xml:id="table_unitconversions">
				<title>Unit Conversions</title>
				<tabular>
					<row>
					<cell>
						<term>Length</term>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1 foot (ft) = 12 inches (in)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						1 yard (yd) = 3 feet (ft)
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1 mile = 5,280 feet
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1000 millimeters (mm) = 1 meter (m)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						100 centimeters (cm) = 1 meter
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1000 meters (m) = 1 kilometer (km)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						2.54 centimeters (cm) = 1 inch
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						<term>Weight and Mass</term>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1 pound (lb) = 16 ounces (oz)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						1 ton = 2000 pounds
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1000 milligrams (mg) = 1 gram (g)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						1000 grams = 1 kilogram (kg)
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1 kilogram = 2.2 pounds (on Earth)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						<term>Capacity</term>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1 cup = 8 fluid ounces (fl oz)*
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						1 pint = 2 cups
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1 quart = 2 pints = 4 cups
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						1 gallon = 4 quarts = 16 cups
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
						1000 milliliters (ml) = 1 liter (L)
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					<cell>
					</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>

			<p>
				*Fluid ounces are a capacity measurement for liquids. 1 fluid ounce <m>\approx</m> 1 ounce (weight) for water only.
			</p>

			<video youtube="fyOcLcIVipM"/> <!-- Proportions with unit conversion-->

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates16">
				<statement>
					<p>
						A bicycle is traveling at 15 miles per hour. How many feet will it cover in 20 seconds?
					</p>
					<p>
						To answer this question, we need to convert 20 seconds into feet. If we know the speed of the bicycle in feet per second, this question would be simpler. Since we don’t, we will need to do additional unit conversions. We will need to know that 5280 ft = 1 mile. We might start by converting the 20 seconds into hours: <md><mrow> 20\text{ seconds}\cdot \frac{1\text{ minute}}{60\text{ seconds}}\cdot\frac{1\text{ hour}}{60\text{ minutes}} &amp;= \frac{1}{180}\text{ hour} &amp; \text{Now we can multiply by the 15 miles/hr}</mrow><mrow>\frac{1}{180}\text{ hour} \cdot \frac{15\text{ miles}}{1\text{ hour}} &amp;= \frac{1}{12}\text{ mile} &amp; \text{Now we can convert to feet}</mrow><mrow> \frac{1}{12}\text{ mile} \cdot \frac{5280\text{ feet}}{1\text{ mile}} &amp;= 440\text{ feet}</mrow></md>
					</p>

					<p>
						We could have also done this entire calculation in one long set of products: <me> 20\text{ seconds}\cdot \frac{1\text{ minute}}{60\text{ seconds}} \cdot \frac{1\text{ hour}}{60\text{ minutes}} \cdot \frac{15\text{ miles}}{1\text{ hour}}\cdot \frac{5280\text{ feet}}{1\text{ mile}} = 440\text{ feet}.</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<problem xml:id="tin_rates4">
				<statement>
					<p>
						A 1000 foot spool of bare 12-gauge copper wire weighs 19.8 pounds. How much will 18 inches of the wire weigh, in ounces?
					</p>
				</statement>
				<answer>
					<p>
						<me>18\text{ inches}\cdot \frac{1\text{ foot}}{12\text{ inches}} \cdot \frac{19.8\text{ pounds}}{1000\text{ feet}} \cdot \frac{16\text{ ounces}}{1\text{ pound}} \approx 0.475\text{ ounces}.</me>
					</p>
				</answer>
			</problem>

			<p>
				Notice that with the miles per gallon example, if we double the miles driven, we double the gas used. Likewise, with the map distance example, if the map distance doubles, the real-life distance doubles. This is a key feature of proportional relationships, and one we must confirm before assuming two things are related proportionally.
			</p>

			<video youtube="-e2typcrhLE"/> <!-- Considering how/if things scale -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates17">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Suppose you’re tiling the floor of a 10 ft by 10 ft room, and find that 100 tiles will be needed. How many tiles will be needed to tile the floor of a 20 ft by 20 ft room?
					</p>
					<p>
						In this case, while the width the room has doubled, the area has quadrupled. Since the number of tiles needed corresponds with the area of the floor, not the width, 400 tiles will be needed. We could find this using a proportion based on the areas of the rooms: <me>\frac{100\text{ tiles}}{100\text{ ft}^2} = \frac{n\text{ tiles}}{400\text{ ft}^2}.</me>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<p>
				Other quantities just don’t scale proportionally at all.
			</p>

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates18">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Suppose a small company spends $1000 on an advertising campaign, and gains 100 new customers from it. How many new customers should they expect if they spend $10,000?
					</p>

					<p>
						While it is tempting to say that they will gain 1000 new customers, it is likely that additional advertising will be less effective than the initial advertising. For example, if the company is a hot tub store, there are likely only a fixed number of people interested in buying a hot tub, so there might not even be 1000 people in the town who would be potential customers.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<p>
				Sometimes when working with rates, proportions, and percents, the process can be made more challenging by the magnitude of the numbers involved. Sometimes, large numbers are just difficult to comprehend.
			</p>

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates19">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Compare the 2010 U.S. military budget of $683.7 billion to other quantities.
					</p>

					<p>
						Here we have a very large number, about $683,700,000,000 written out. Of course, imagining a billion dollars is very difficult, so it can help to compare it to other quantities.
					</p>

					<p>
						If that amount of money was used to pay the salaries of the 1.4 million Walmart employees in the U.S., each would earn over $488,000.
					</p>

					<p>
						There are about 300 million people in the U.S. The military budget is about $2,200 per person.
					</p>

					<p>
						If you were to put $683.7 billion in $100 bills, and count out 1 per second, it would take 216 years to finish counting it.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>
			
			<video youtube="rCLh8ZvSQr8"/> <!-- Comparing quantities involving large numbers -->

			<remark xml:id="ex_rates20">
				<statement>
					<p>
						Compare the electricity consumption per capita in China to the rate in Japan.
					</p>

					<p>
						To address this question, we will first need data. From the CIA website (<url href="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2042rank.html">Source</url>) we can find the electricity consumption in 2011 for China was 4,693,000,000,000 KWH (kilowatt-hours), or 4.693 trillion KWH, while the consumption for Japan was 859,700,000,000, or 859.7 billion KWH. To find the rate per capita (per person), we will also need the population of the two countries. 
					</p>
					<p>	From the World Bank (<url href="http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.TOTL">Source</url>), we can find the population of China is 1,344,130,000, or 1.344 billion, and the population of Japan is 127,817,277, or 127.8 million.
					</p>

					<p>
						Computing the consumption per capita for each country:
						<md>
							<mrow>\text{China:} &amp; \frac{4,693,000,000,000\text{ KWH}}{1,344,130,000\text{ people}} &amp;\approx 3491.5\text{ KWH per person}</mrow>
							<mrow>\text{Japan:} &amp; \frac{859,700,000,000\text{ KWH}}{127,817,277\text{ people}} &amp;\approx 6726\text{ KWH per person}</mrow>
						</md>
					</p>
					<p>
						While China uses more than 5 times the electricity of Japan overall, because the population of Japan is so much smaller, it turns out Japan uses almost twice the electricity per person compared to China.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</remark>

			<exercises xml:id="exercises_proportions"> <!-- 27 through 50 -->
				<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Find a unit rate: You bought 10 pounds of potatoes for $4.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Find a unit rate: Joel ran 1500 meters in 4 minutes, 45 seconds.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Solve: <m>\displaystyle\frac{2}{5} = \displaystyle\frac{6}{x}.</m>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Solve: <m>\displaystyle\frac{n}{5} = \displaystyle\frac{16}{20}.</m>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A crepe recipe calls for 2 eggs, 1 cup of flour, and 1 cup of milk. How much flour would you need if you use 5 eggs?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							An 8ft length of 4 inch wide crown molding costs $14. How much will it cost to buy 40ft of crown molding?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Four 3-megawatt wind turbines can supply enough electricity to power 3000 homes. How many turbines would be required to power 55,000 homes?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A highway had a landslide, where 3,000 cubic yards of material fell on the road, requiring 200 dump truck loads to clear. On another highway, a slide left 40,000 cubic yards on the road. How many dump truck loads would be needed to clear this slide?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Convert 8 feet to inches.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Convert 6 kilograms to grams.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A wire costs $2 per meter. How much will 3 kilometers of wire cost?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Sugar contains 15 calories per teaspoon. How many calories are in 1 cup of sugar?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A car is driving at 100 kilometers per hour. How far does it travel in 2 seconds?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A chain weighs 10 pounds per foot. How many ounces will 4 inches weigh?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The table below gives data on three movies. Gross earnings is the amount of money the movie brings in. Compare the net earnings (money made after expenses) for the three movies. (<url href="http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/records/budgets.php">Source</url>)
						</p>
						<table>
							<tabular>
								<row bottom="medium">
								<cell>
									Movie
								</cell>
								<cell>
									Release Date
								</cell>
								<cell>
									Budget
								</cell>
								<cell>
									Gross Earnings
								</cell>
								</row>
								<row>
								<cell>
									Saw
								</cell>
								<cell>
									10/29/2004
								</cell>
								<cell>
									$1,200,000
								</cell>
								<cell>
									$103,096,345
								</cell>
								</row>
								<row>
								<cell>
									Titanic
								</cell>
								<cell>
									12/19/1997
								</cell>
								<cell>
									$200,000,000
								</cell>
								<cell>
									$1,842,879,955
								</cell>
								</row>
								<row>
								<cell>
									Jurassic Park
								</cell>
								<cell>
									6/11/1993
								</cell>
								<cell>
									$63,000,000
								</cell>
								<cell>
									$923,83,984
								</cell>
								</row>
							</tabular>
						</table>

					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							For the movies in the previous problem, which provided the best return on investment?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The population of the U.S. is about 309,975,000, covering a land area of 3,717,000 square miles. The population of India is about 1,184,639,000, covering a land area of 1,269,000 square miles. Compare the population densities of the two countries.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The GDP (Gross Domestic Product) of China was $5,739 billion in 2010, and the GDP of Sweden was $435 billion. The population of China is about 1,347 million, while the population of Sweden is about 9.5 million. Compare the GDP per capita of the two countries.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							In June 2012, Twitter was reporting 400 million tweets per day. Each tweet can consist of up to 140 characters (letter, numbers, etc.). Create a comparison to help understand the amount of tweets in a year by imagining each character was a drop of water and comparing to filling something up.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The photo sharing site Flickr had 2.7 billion photos in June 2012. Create a comparison to understand this number by assuming each picture is about 2 megabytes in size, and comparing to the data stored on other media like DVDs, iPods, or flash drives.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							Your chocolate milk mix says to use 4 scoops of mix for 2 cups of milk. After pouring in the milk, you start adding the mix, but get distracted and accidentally put in 5 scoops of mix. How can you adjust the mix if:
							<ol>
								<li>
									<p>
										There is still room in the cup?
									</p>
								</li>
								<li>
									<p>
										The cup is already full?
									</p>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							A recipe for sabayon calls for 2 egg yolks, 3 tablespoons of sugar, and <m>\frac14</m> cup of white wine. After cracking the eggs, you start measuring the sugar, but accidentally put in 4 tablespoons of sugar. How can you compensate?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The Deepwater Horizon oil spill resulted in 4.9 million barrels of oil spilling into the Gulf of Mexico. Each barrel of oil can be processed into about 19 gallons of gasoline. How many cars could this have fueled for a year? Assume an average car gets 20 miles to the gallon, and drives about 12,000 miles in a year.
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
							<exercise>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The store is selling lemons at 2 for $1. Each yields about 2 tablespoons of juice. How much will it cost to buy enough lemons to make a 9-inch lemon pie requiring <m>\frac12</m> cup of lemon juice?
						</p>
					</statement>
				</exercise>
			</exercises>
		</section> <!-- Rates and proportions -->



</chapter>